这是「小镇有灵」，一个像素风格的、集成大语言模型的生活模拟原型。
This is "Living Town", a pixel-style life-simulation prototype built around a large language model.
核心设计是：确定性引擎当地板，大语言模型只当声音。即使没有任何模型，小镇也能照常运转。
Core design: a deterministic engine as the floor, the LLM only as a voice. Even with no model at all, the town keeps living.
屏幕上的每个居民，都有需求、作息、性格、记忆，以及与他人的关系。
Every resident here has needs, routines, personality, memory, and relationships with others.
两轮架构评审——内部多智能体评审，与 GPT-5.5——都指向同一个致命缺陷：引擎里原本没有任何居民之间的交互。
Two rounds of review, an internal multi-agent panel and GPT-5.5, found the same fatal gap: the engine had no agent-to-agent interaction.
所以我们先把社交，做成一等的确定性能力：打招呼、送礼、传八卦，都走同一套社交事务协议。
So we first made social interaction a first-class deterministic capability: greeting, gifting, and gossip all flow through one social-transaction protocol.
每次互动都会发起、被接受或被拒绝，然后提交；双方和旁观者，各自写下视角不同的记忆。
Each interaction is proposed, accepted or refused, then committed; both parties and bystanders record memories from different viewpoints.
八卦只能通过交谈或亲眼所见传播。这就是知识边界：没人会凭空知道一个秘密。
Gossip spreads only by talking or witnessing. This is the knowledge boundary: nobody learns a secret out of thin air.
在社交之上，是承诺系统。居民们会约定，稍后在某处见面。
Above social interaction sits the commitment system. Residents agree to meet somewhere later.
临近约定时间，他们会主动赴约；可一旦某项需求陷入危机，就可能爽约。
As the deadline nears, they head to the rendezvous; but if a need hits crisis, they may flake.
爽约会埋下怨气。怨气累积到一定程度，就会触发一段冲突。
Flaking plants resentment. Once it builds up enough, a conflict is triggered.
冲突有完整的生命周期：积怨、当面对质、道歉、和解，或者久拖不决，变成冷战。
Conflicts have a full lifecycle: resentment, confrontation, apology, reconciliation, or, left alone, a lingering cold war.
你在左下角日志里看到的「把话说开」和「两人和解」，全是零模型、确定性地涌现出来的。
The phrases in the log at bottom-left, clearing the air and reconciling, all emerge deterministically, with zero model.
所有逻辑都先用 Node 端口验证，再回写 Godot，并在真实引擎里跑通：十三条不变量，跨多个随机种子，全部通过。
All logic is first validated in a Node port, ported back to Godot, and run in the real engine: thirteen invariants, across many seeds, all passing.
为了让小镇不再简陋，地面、草木和房屋都换上了 CC0 像素素材，并叠加了昼夜光照。
To make the town less bare, the ground, foliage and houses now use free CC0 pixel art, with a day-night lighting cycle layered on top.
居民相遇时，会在头顶冒出对话和心情。这些台词目前是模板，将来交给模型生成。
When residents meet, dialogue and mood pop up over their heads. These lines are templates for now, to be generated by the model later.
你可以暂停、加速、缩放，还能拖动底部的时间轴，确定性地回放任意时刻。
You can pause, speed up, zoom, and drag the timeline at the bottom to deterministically replay any moment.
点选任意居民，就能像观察演化一样，查看他此刻的需求、关系、信念与记忆。
Click any resident and, like an evolution observatory, inspect their needs, relationships, beliefs and memories at that very moment.
确定性的地基，已经就绪。下一步，才是让大语言模型，为这些有灵魂的居民，赋予真正的声音。
The deterministic foundation is ready. Next, we let the language model give these living residents their true voice.